Guide to the Max S. Baucus Papers 1958-2016 (bulk 1974-2014)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Max S. Baucus Papers
1944-2016 (bulk 1974-2014)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 862
Baucus, Max S. (Max Sieben), b. 1941
937.4 linear feet 808 microfilm reels 21 oversized items 149 artifacts 913.66 gigabytes of digital material
Max Baucus was a Montana congressman who served in the Montana House of Representatives from 1973 to 1974, the U.S. House of Representatives from 1975 to 1978, and the U.S. Senate from 1978 to 2014, and served as the U.S. Ambassador to China from 2014 to 2016. This collection includes administrative files, constituent correspondence, sponsored and cosponsored bills, floor and hearing statements, committee files, voting records, legislative subject files, press materials, and campaign files and ephemera, as well as some personal material.
Biographical Note
Max Sieben Baucus (born Enke) was born on December 11, 1941 at St. Peter's Hospital in Helena, Montana, to Stephen Enke and Jean Sheriff. His sister, Karen, was born two years later in Stanford, California. The Enkes separated and Jean moved with Max and Karen back to Montana. Jean married John J. Baucus Jr., a former Air Force officer, in March of 1947. Max Baucus spent the remainder of his childhood in Helena, while spending summers and weekends at the Sieben family ranch. Baucus’ first foray into public service took the shape of his participation in the American Legion Montana Boys State in 1958, where he was elected Most Outstanding Citizen. This appointment led to his nomination as one of two Montana representatives to the American Legion Boys Nation in Washington, D.C. in 1959, where he met Senators James Murray and Mike Mansfield, and Representatives Lee Metcalf and LeRoy H. Anderson. After graduating from high school in 1959, Baucus attended Carleton College in Minnesota for one year. He then transferred to Stanford University, where he graduated in 1964 with a B.A. in Economics. During his time at Stanford, Baucus spent a year traveling internationally, a trip which was to significantly shape his world view and spark a desire for a career in public service. He subsequently received an L.L.B. from Stanford University Law School in 1967.
Baucus moved to Washington, D.C. after law school, where he spent three years working as a lawyer for the Securities and Exchange Commission. It was there that he first met with Senator Mike Mansfield to discuss the idea of running for office. He moved to Missoula, Montana in 1971 to practice law. He was a staff member for the Montana Constitutional Convention, first as the Executive Assistant to Leo Graybill, Jr., President of the Constitutional Convention, and then as the Executive Director. Baucus was elected to the Montana House of Representatives in 1972, representing Missoula. He conducted his first Congressional campaign in 1975, beating incumbent Dick Shoup to win a seat in the U.S. House of Representatives. Baucus served two terms in the House, from 1975-1978, and was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1978.
As the longest-serving U.S. Senator from Montana, Baucus served in the Senate from 1978 to 2014, winning six consecutive elections. During that time, he served nearly 10 years as Chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, as well as two years as Chairman of the Environment and Public Works Committee. He also served on the Senate Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Small Business, and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition and Forestry. Significant legislative accomplishments include amendments to the Wild and Scenic Rivers Act in 1976; tax reform efforts in the 1980s and 2000s; the Clean Air Act Amendments of 1990; the Transportation Equity Act for the 21st Century (TEA-21) of 1998; the Rocky Mountain Front Heritage Act of 2013; securing federal recognition and support for the asbestos crisis in Libby, Montana; and the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (ACA) of 2010. Baucus was a strong advocate for rural communities throughout his tenure in both the House and Senate, introducing and supporting legislation surrounding rural health care, postal service, and air service. He also worked extensively on trade issues, and was deeply involved in negotiations regarding softwood lumber imports from Canada, beef imports from Japan, and the assignation of China’s Most Favored Nation status. Locally, Baucus founded and facilitated the triennial Montana Economic Development Summit from 2000 to 2013, a jobs summit which brought together Montana residents and renowned business leaders from around the globe.
President Barack Obama nominated Baucus to the post of United States Ambassador to the People’s Republic of China on January 7, 2014. Baucus’ nomination was subsequently confirmed by the Senate on February 6, 2014, and he assumed his ambassadorial duties on March 20, 2014. He served as Ambassador until January 20, 2017. Baucus currently resides in Montana.
This collection, the Max S. Baucus Papers, represents the material sum of Max Baucus’s political career, from his work at the Montana Constitutional Convention to his appointment as the United States Ambassador to China. It includes manuscript materials, artifacts and memorabilia, microfilm, audiovisual material, photographs, and electronic records produced throughout Baucus’s time in the Montana House of Representatives, the United States House of Representatives, the Senate, and ambassadorial service. These records document policy and legislation development, constituent services, Baucus’s committee service, political campaigns, his membership in the Democratic Party, and office administration. Particularly well-represented are Senate legislative materials, as well as constituent correspondence from his time in both the House and the Senate.
The collection also includes some material from Baucus’s personal life which provides a small snapshot of his daily and social activities throughout his time in public service. This material primarily takes the form of photographs, ephemera, miscellaneous correspondence and holiday cards, invitations, and notebooks.
This collection has been arranged into 16 series, many of which contain subseries.
Series I: Personal, 1958-2014 and undated, 7.9 linear feet, 2.9 MB - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Personal, 1958-2014, 7.9 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Electronic Files, 1994-2010, 2.9 MB - RESTRICTED
Series II: Montana House of Representatives, 1972-1974, 3.3 linear feet
Series III: U.S. House of Representatives: Office, 1974-1978, 4 linear feet, 1.2 MB
Subseries 1: Administrative Files, 1974-1978, 1.1 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Scheduling Materials, 1975-1978, 2.9 linear feet
Subseries 3: Electronic Files, 1977, 1.2 MB - RESTRICTED
Series IV: U.S. House of Representatives: Press, 1974-1978, 3.9 linear feet, 531.4 MB
Subseries 1: Press Materials, 1974-1978, 0.2 linear feet
Subseries 2: Press Clips and Press Releases, 1974-1978, 2.6 linear feet
Subseries 3: Speeches, 1975-1978, 1.1 linear feet
Subseries 4: Electronic Files, 1975-1978, 531.4 MB
Series V: U.S. House of Representatives: Constituent Correspondence, 1974-1978, 59.3 linear feet, 9 microfilm reels
Series VI: U.S. House of Representatives: Legislative, 1974-1979, 16.2 linear feet, 76.3 MB
Subseries 1: Sponsored/Cosponsored Bills, 1975-1978, 5.6 linear feet
Subseries 2: Floor Statements, 1975-1978, 0.7 linear feet
Subseries 3: Congressional Profile, 1975-1979, 0.8 linear feet
Subseries 4: Committee Files, 1975-1979, 2.8 linear feet
Subseries 5: Subject Files, 1975-1978, 6.3 linear feet
Subseries 6: Electronic Files, 1975-1978, 76.3 MB
Series VII: Senate: Office, 1979-2014, 24.1 linear feet, 2.1 GB
Subseries 1: Administrative Files, 1979-2014, 8.7 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Scheduling Materials, 1979-2014, 8.7 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 3: Electronic Files, 2001-2014, 2.1 GB - RESTRICTED
Series VIII: Senate: Press, 1978-2014, 41.4 linear feet, 15.3 GB
Subseries 1: Press Clips, 1978-2014, 23.6 linear feet
Subseries 2: Press Releases, 1979-2014, 11.8 linear feet
Subseries 3: Speeches, 1979-2013, 5.9 linear feet
Subseries 4: Miscellaneous, 1980-2011, 0.1 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 5: Electronic Files, 1978-2014, 15.3 GB
Series IX: Senate: Constituent Correspondence, 1979-2014, 484.4 linear feet, 799 microfilm reels, 89.8 GB - - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Constituent Correspondence, 1979-2014, 478.8 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Petitions, 2008-2013, 5.6 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 3: Microfilm, 1979-1988, 799 microfilm reels - RESTRICTED
Subseries 4: Electronic Files, 1979-2014, 89.8 GB - RESTRICTED
Series X: Senate: Legislative, 1975-2014 and undated, 256.1 linear feet, 45.7 GB
Subseries 1: Sponsored and Cosponsored Bills, 1979-2015, 9.5 linear feet
Subseries 2: Floor Statements, 1979-2014, 9.8 linear feet
Subseries 3: Congressional Profile, 1979-2014, 43.6 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 4: Voting Record, 1977-2013, 4.2 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 5: Committee Files, 1979-2014, 8.7 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 6: Subject Files, 1975-2014, 126.3 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 7: Libby Files, 1999-2010, 4.4 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 8: Staff Files, 1979-2014, 49.6 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 9: Electronic Files, 1979-2014, 45.7 GB - RESTRICTED
Series XI: Campaign, 1968-2013 and undated, 5.9 linear feet, 21 oversize items, 290.1 MB - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Montana House of Representatives, 1972-circa 1973, 0.1 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: U.S. House of Representatives, 1974-1977, 0.7 linear feet, 1 oversized item - RESTRICTED
Subseries 3: Senate, 1968-2013, 5.1 linear feet, 20 oversized items - RESTRICTED
Subseries 4: Audiovisual, 1955-2008, 120 audio recordings, 299 video recordings - RESTRICTED
Subseries 5: Electronic Files, 2000-2002, 290.1 MB - RESTRICTED
Series XII: Political, 1971-2015, 1 linear feet - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Political, 1971-2015, 1.0 linear foot - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Electronic Files, 1972-2003, 4.7 MB - RESTRICTED
Series XIII: Photographs, 1958-2014 and undated, 26.7 linear feet, 14 negatives boxes, 281.9 GB
Subseries 1: Photographs, 1959-2013, 25.7 linear feet
Subseries 2: Accession 2017-042, 1962-2008, 0.3 linear feet
Subseries 3: Accession 2018-043, 1978-2008, 0.4 linear feet
Subseries 4: Photographic Negatives,1982-2003, 3.2 linear feet
Subseries 5: Electronic Files, 1958-2014, 282 GB
Sub-Subseries 1: U.S. House of Representatives, 1975-1978, 2.40 GB
Sub-Subseries 2: Senate, 1958-2014, 279.0 GB
Sub-Subseries 3: Accession 2019-033, 2007-2011, 565.7 MB
Series XIV: Audiovisual, 1955-2014 and undated, 959 audio and video recordings, 475.1 GB - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Audio Recordings, 1978-2008, 203 audio recordings - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Video Recordings, 1955-2014, 756 video recordings - RESTRICTED
Subseries 3: Electronic Files, 1976-2014, 475.1 GB - RESTRICTED
Series XV: Memorabilia, 1944-circa 2016, 149 artifacts, 1.8 GB - RESTRICTED
Subseries 1: Artifacts, 1944-circa 2016, 149 artifacts - RESTRICTED
Subseries 2: Electronic Files, 1975-2014, 1.8 GB - RESTRICTED
Series XVI: Ambassadorial, 2013-2017, 1.1 GB - RESTRICTED
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula. All files from Max Baucus' terms in the US Senate - with the exception of press clips, press releases, speeches, floor statements, sponsored and cosponsored bills, and photographs - are fully restricted until 2044.
Materials in this collection were transferred to the Archives by Max Baucus and various staffers, the majority of which were shipped to the Archives from storage at the Washington National Records Center in Suitland, Maryland. The transfer of some electronic records was also facilitated by the Sergeant at Arms of the United States Senate.
This collection was deposited at the University of Montana Archives and Special Collections by the creator, Max S. Baucus, in April 2014. Subsequent accessions were added to the collection in 2015, 2017 and 2018.
A series of oral history interviews were conducted with Max Baucus in 2017 and 2018, and are housed in the Archives and Special Collections at the Mansfield Library (OH 456).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Baucus, Max S. (Max Sieben)--Archives
United States. Congress. House.; Montana. Legislative Assembly. House of Representatives.; United States. Congress. Senate.
United States--Foreign relations--China.; Montana--Politics and government--20th century.
United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--China.
Politics and Politicians; Montana
Ambassadors--United States; Diplomatic and consular service, American--China; Legislators--United States
- Personal, 1958-2014; Series I; 7.9 linear feet; 2.89 megabytes
  Materials in this series provide insight into the personal and family history of Max Baucus. They largely pertain to Baucus’s life outside of politics, though his personal and political lives inevitably overlapped as a career elected official.
  This series is divided into two sub-series: Personal and Electronic Files.
  All materials in this series are restricted until 2044.
  - Personal, 1958-2014; Sub-series 1; 7.9 linear feet
    This subseries represents the physical portion of this series, and contains invitations and materials related to various social events on Capitol Hill which Baucus attended, including Presidential inaugurations and White House events. It also contains a number of appointment books and wallet diaries that provide a window into Baucus’s personal schedule, in contrast to official scheduling material produced by staffers. A nearly complete run of Baucus family Christmas cards is also included, several of which feature artwork created by Baucus’s second wife, Wanda Minge.
    Correspondence found within this series is largely comprised of letters marked ‘Administration-Personal’ by office staff, though there are letters relating to specific incidents in Baucus’s life. The series also includes personal notes and notebooks kept by Baucus throughout his career, containing notes and observations taken during meetings, hearings, and other events, reflections on various topical issues, draft ideas for speeches, and campaign strategies. Many of these are undated. The series likewise contains a number of writings and publications authored by Baucus, including op-eds and two peer-reviewed papers. Also notable is a pocket Constitution given to Baucus by Senator Robert Byrd in 1995, which he carried with him throughout the remainder of his Senate career.
    While largely comprised of material focusing on Baucus’s personal life, the series does contain some records relating to his family—chiefly obituaries following the death of Baucus’s stepfather, John Baucus, and correspondence between Jean Baucus and Ruth Chambers. Chambers was the sister of Max Baucus’s biological father, Stephen Enke, and the correspondence took place between Jean Baucus and Chambers following Enke’s death in 1974. The series also contains a Baucus family tree and family recipes.
    Files are arranged alphabetically.
    All materials in this sub-series are restricted until 2044.
  - Electronic Files, 1994-2010; Sub-series 2; 2.9 megabytes
    This subseries contains essays and op-eds authored by Baucus, as well as a 1983 New York City Marathon athlete profile sheet. Files have been renamed for clarity by the processing archivist.
    Essay and op-ed files are arranged chronologically.
- Montana House of Representatives, 1972-1974; Series II; 3.3 linear feet
  This series contains material relating to Max Baucus’s time in the Montana House of Representatives. It includes press files, bills which were sponsored or cosponsored by Baucus, voting records, and subject files. Subject files constitute the majority of this series, and consist of documents created and kept by Baucus and his staff during the course of their legislative work. Materials contained within subject files include correspondence, research materials, memos, notes, reports, and other related items reflecting the pertinent political and legislative issues of the time. Staffers assigned subjects according to a topical index. This index helped to organize many administrative functions, including legislative research, the tracking of constituent opinion, the compilation of Baucus’s legislative achievements, and responses to constituent concerns.
  Subject files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Press Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1A/1)
  - Press Clippings, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1A/2)
  - Press materials, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/1)
  - Walter Mondale, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/2)
  - Sponsored and Cosponsored Bills, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/3)
  - Voting Records, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/4)
  - Voting Records, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/5)
  - Non-sponsored Bills, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/6)
  - Subject Files - Agriculture, 1972-1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/7)
  - Subject Files - Agriculture, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/8)
  - Subject Files - Agriculture, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/9)
  - Subject Files - Banking, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/10)
  - Subject Files - Banking, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/11)
  - Subject Files - Campaign Reform, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 1/12)
  - Subject Files - Campaign Reform, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/1)
  - Subject Files - Businesses, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/2)
  - Subject Files - Crime, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/3)
  - Subject Files - Defense, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/4)
  - Subject Files - Defense - Minuteman missiles, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/5)
  - Subject Files - Drugs, Alcohol and Tobacco, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/6)
  - Subject Files - Drugs, Alcohol and Tobacco, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/7)
  - Subject Files - Economy, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/8)
  - Subject Files - Economy, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/9)
  - Subject Files - Economy, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 2/10)
  - Subject Files - Economy, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/1)
  - Subject Files - Education, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/2)
  - Subject Files - Education, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/3)
  - Subject Files - Education, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/4)
  - Subject Files - Education, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/5)
  - Subject Files - Environment, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/6)
  - Subject Files - Environment, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/7)
  - Subject Files - Environment, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 3/8)
  - Subject Files - Environment, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/1)
  - Subject Files - Environment, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/2)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Air pollution, 1972-1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/3)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Energy crisis, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/4)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Missouri River Basin, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/5)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Montana land use policy study, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/6)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Montana Rangeland Resource Program, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/7)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Noise pollution, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/8)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Northern Plains, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/9)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Northern Plains, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 4/10)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Project Plan: Headwaters Resource Conservation and Development (RC and D) Montana, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/1)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Saline Alkali Correction Act, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/2)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Solid waste, 1972 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/3)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Strip mining and coal, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/4)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Strip mining and coal, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/5)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Water use and coal development in Eastern Montana, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/6)
  - Subject Files - Environment - Wilderness, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/7)
  - Subject Files - Federal Government, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/8)
  - Subject Files - Foreign Policy, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/9)
  - Subject Files - Forestry, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 5/10)
  - Subject Files - Forestry, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/1)
  - Subject Files - Gambling, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/2)
  - Subject Files - Healthcare, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/3)
  - Subject Files - Healthcare, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/4)
  - Subject Files - Healthcare - Child development, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/5)
  - Subject Files - Healthcare - Mental health, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/6)
  - Subject Files - Housing, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/7)
  - Subject Files - Insurance, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/8)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Court reform, 1972 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/9)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Equal Rights Amendment, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/10)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Equal Rights Amendment, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/11)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Joint tenancy, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/12)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Legislative role structures, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/13)
  - Subject Files - Judiciary - Montana Bar Association, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 6/14)
  - Subject Files - Labor, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/1)
  - Subject Files - Labor - United Automobile Workers, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/2)
  - Subject Files - Labor - Workmen's compensation, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/3)
  - Subject Files - Native Americans, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/4)
  - Subject Files - Native Americans, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/5)
  - Subject Files - Native Americans - Montana Inter-Tribal Policy Board, October 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/6)
  - Subject Files - Native Americans - Preprofessional engineering studies for reservation Indian students, July 3, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/7)
  - Subject Files - Native Americans - Profile of the Montana Native American, August 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/8)
  - Subject Files - Senior Citizens, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 7/9)
  - Subject Files - Senior Citizens, 1973-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/1)
  - Subject Files - State Government, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/2)
  - Subject Files - State Government, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/3)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Ombudsman proposal, 1972-1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/4)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Governor Annual Report, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/5)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Whip advisories, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/6)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Public forums, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/7)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Common Cause, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/8)
  - Subject Files - State Government - Conflicts of interest, 1972 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/9)
  - Subject Files - Taxation, 1974 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/10)
  - Subject Files - Watergate, 1973 (Box-folder Series 2 - 8/11)
- U.S. House of Representatives: Office, 1974-1978; Series III; 4.0 linear feet; 1.2 megabytes